Good morning, everyone. If you don't know me, my name is Sam. I'm a resident pastor here.
It's my honor to share God's Word with us this morning. We're going to continue in this sermon
series called Bible Shorts, where we're going through shorter books of the Bible during the
summer, and we're starting a new section where we're going to be looking at the book of 2 Thessalonians.
And so if you could turn your Bible or whatever device you read the Bible on to 2 Thessalonians,
we're going to do that for this week, next week, and the week afterwards. There's three
chapters in that book. And as we, as we're turning to 2 Thessalonians, I want to share just a short
story with you. A couple years ago, Sangin and I, we, after we got married for our honeymoon, we went
to a bunch of national parks around Las Vegas. And you probably don't know this about me, but I am
pretty afraid of heights. And so we're going to all these national parks, we're doing all these
hikes. And so most of the time, this is what I looked like, at least internally. We're doing all
these hikes. It's like beautiful landscape. I mean, like Sian took that picture up there, and I was
like, that's beautiful. I know I would be so scared if I was there. And for most of the trip, that's how
I felt internally. But I still managed to do most of the hikes we went on, except for one. In Zion
National Park, there's a hike called Angel's Landing. You can show a picture here. And at the
very tip of Angel's Landing, there's like, I don't know, like it's like a hundred yards to get to the
very peak. And it's like, there's a, you have to like use this chain to get to the top. Yeah, good,
side by side. And I like, I chickened out. And like, Sung Young tried for like a long time. She's
like, come on, we're here. We're only gonna do this once. We're never gonna do this again. And I was
like, no, like, I can't do it. I want to, but I can't. I'm too scared. I'm not going to do it.
You know, I found out while preparing for the sermon, like, unfortunately, people have died
on this landing. And so now I feel justified for this. But anyway, this is the one hike I couldn't
do. You know, I was just unwilling to do it because I was so scared. And I remember on the
way down, like, small feelings of regret. Like, man, did I miss out on something that would have
been worthwhile because I was unwilling to face my fear. Like, was there something that I could
have tasted, but because of my unwillingness, I missed out on it? And I share this story because
I think in a way this reflects our Christian lives. You know, who among us here doesn't want
a more rich life in the Lord? I'm sure there's many of us here who want the fullness of joy and
the fullness of life that we can have in walking with God, a deeper confidence in his word, growing
love for one another, a steadfastness in your faith. I'm sure there's many people here who would
want that. But what if that kind of full, rich life in the Lord required suffering or persecution?
As we look at 2 Thessalonians today, what we're going to talk about is suffering and persecution
and how we can face that as Christians.
Like I said, there's three chapters to the book of 2 Thessalonians.
So today we're going to be talking about suffering and persecution.
Next week we'll talk about Jesus' coming and confusion around that.
And last week we're going to talk about the issue of idleness.
And throughout the whole book, there's this kind of backdrop theme of Jesus' return.
And as we think about Jesus' return and as we think about the richness of Christian life
that we might be missing out on,
I think we're going to see that for some of us,
this might be one of the reasons that we aren't experiencing all that God has for us
because we're unwilling to face suffering, pain, and persecution.
But as we look into this chapter, what we're going to see
is that Jesus gives us hope to face these things.
That's why the one thing for today is that Jesus' return
gives us hope to face persecution and live more fully for God.
That Jesus' return gives us hope to face persecution
and live more fully for God.
Please join me as I read 2 Thessalonians chapter 1,
the whole thing from 1 through verse 12.
This is what it says in the ESV.
It says,
your steadfastness and faith in all your persecutions and in the afflictions that you are
enduring. This is evidence of the righteous judgment of God that you may be considered
worthy of the kingdom of God for which you are also suffering. Since indeed God considers
it just to replay with affliction those who afflict you and to grant relief to you who
are afflicted as well as to us when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with his mighty
angels in flaming fire, inflicting vengeance on those who do not know God and on those
who do not obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus.
They will suffer the punishment of eternal destruction
away from the presence of the Lord
and from the glory of his might
when he comes on that day to be glorified in his saints
and to be marveled at among all who have believed
because our testimony to you was believed.
To this end, we always pray for you
that our God may make you worthy of his calling
and may fulfill every resolve for good
and every work of faith by his power
so that the name of our Lord Jesus
may be glorified in you
and you in him according to the grace of our God
and the Lord Jesus Christ.
Please join me as we pray and go into this word together.
Father, we come to you and Lord, we do ask
that even as we are here gathered this morning
that you would meet us today.
That as we look into your word,
your Holy Spirit would move in our hearts and speak to us.
Lord, we ask that you would give us openness,
that you would give us faith,
that you would give us resolve.
That what you speak to us about,
not only that it would cut us to the heart,
but that you would help us to respond in a way that is pleasing to you.
We thank you for your faithfulness and goodness to us.
We pray all these things in Jesus' name. Amen.
Amen. As we go into this chapter, just some background information about the book of 2 Thessalonians.
Many of us know this is a letter that was written to the church in Thessalonica.
It's a church that was in Greece. It's still in Greece today, second largest city in Greece.
But there was a church there that had formed.
In Acts 17, you see an account of what happened.
Paul and some of his traveling companions, they go to the city.
They're there for at least about three weeks.
Paul is preaching and teaching the gospel,
and they see people come to know Christ and be saved.
There's Jews who are saved.
There's Greeks that are saved.
Luke tells us that there's a number of leading women in the city who are saved.
So there's good fruit that is happening,
but they face opposition so much that they're run out of town
and so much that these people who are opposing them chase them from town to town
because they're so angry at them.
And so because of that, Paul writes a letter to them, 1 Thessalonians.
He's like worried. We were only there for like three weeks.
Are you guys okay? Are you guys maturing? Are you guys still there?
And he's happy to find out that they're doing okay.
And this letter is a response to some of the things that came up after that first letter.
And as we look into this passage, the first thing that we're going to see
as we think about how Jesus' return gives us hope for facing persecution
the first thing we're going to see is that knowing God changes our perspective of persecution.
That knowing God changes our perspective of persecution.
So much of Christian life is learning to see things the way God sees them.
That's why Paul writes in Romans 12, verse 2,
that we have to be transformed by the renewing of our minds.
And then the Bible is the primary way through which we get to see and understand things
through God's lens and perspective.
And so just for us to get on the same page here,
we're going to try to see and change,
align our perspectives of suffering and persecution
to how the Bible shows it to us.
Just to be on the same page,
Paul uses three words here to describe what's going on.
He talks about persecution,
which is specifically when people are doing you harm
because of your faith.
Then he uses the word affliction,
which just talks about suffering in general
that is happening because of your faith.
And then he uses the kind of a summary word, suffering.
All of these things, though, he's talking about pain and difficulty that people face because they are walking with the Lord.
And when we think about persecution, in the Bible, the way persecution is presented to us
is that living a faithful Christian life always brings with it the potential for persecution.
Throughout the New Testament, that's what, you know, you see Jesus talks about it.
In John, he says, you know, you will have tribulation in this world as you follow me.
In Matthew, he talks about, blessed are those who are persecuted on my behalf.
Paul talks about it.
In Acts 14, he's telling the disciples in Lystra, Iconium, and Antioch that through many suffering and trials, they will enter the kingdom of God.
In 1 Peter 4, Peter talks about, don't be surprised when you face trials and difficulty and people insult you because of the name of Christ.
Throughout the New Testament, the understanding is that if you're following Jesus faithfully,
there is a potential for persecution and suffering for his namesake.
If you're wondering why that is, our message, the gospel is that there is a God
whose authority is greater than all other authorities and that we are accountable to him.
More than the government, we have to submit and obey God.
More than what the culture says around us, we have to submit and obey God.
More than what your family and friends think, we have to follow and obey God.
And you know what happens?
People in government and in the culture and in your family, they don't like that.
They don't like when you're choosing other things over them.
And so that's often why persecution happens.
And you see it at the governmental level.
You see it in culture.
You see it maybe even relationally in your social spaces.
And that's why that happens.
as we're faithfully seeking to make Christ king over our lives,
it always brings with it this potential that other people will oppose
and push back and seek you harm because they don't like the idea
that there is a God who deserves greater authority than them.
And maybe they don't like the idea that, you know, our hearts are sinful
and that we need salvation.
And so that's what's happening here.
But in this text, we see three positive ways that Paul portrays persecution.
First is that God is praiseworthy in the midst of persecution.
That's the first thing that Paul does in this letter is give thanks to God.
That in the midst of the persecution and affliction that the Thessalonians are experiencing,
he says, it is right, it is appropriate, it is good for us to praise God.
It's probably not the first thing you think about in the midst of persecution,
but here he's saying it is a good thing, and God is worthy to be praised
even in the face of suffering and difficulty and pain.
And then he gives a reason for that.
And the reason here, the second thing is that God is working in the midst of persecution and suffering.
He highlights that the Thessalonians are growing in steadfastness in their faith,
that they're increasing in their love for one another.
And what's not as evident here, like this is what Paul and his friends have been praying for.
In 1 Thessalonians 3, he says,
we have been earnestly praying for y'all day and night. And in verse 13, he says, like, one of the
prayer requests is that we have been praying that you increase in your love for one another, even in
the midst of the opposition and suffering that you are facing. And here in 2 Thessalonians, he's like,
God has answered. God is working among you, that even as you guys face persecution and challenges
and difficulty, that you are growing in your love for one another. Like, God is at work even in the
midst of persecution that is happening. And the last positive thing we see is that God uses
persecution and trials and difficulties to refine and mature his people. He talks about how our
endurance and steadfastness in the midst of persecution is helping us be counted worthy
of the kingdom of God. And this is the interesting, I think, mysterious and joyful part of the gospel
is this idea of the both and, the already and not yet.
And so on one hand, the Thessalonians,
they were counted worthy of God's forgiveness,
of his grace, of being adopted into the family,
of being heirs with Christ when they believed Jesus.
When they believed and turned to Jesus,
on one hand, they were already counted worthy
of all these things.
And yet on the other hand,
they're also being made worthy of these things, right?
It's the connection, but also the distinction
between being justified before God
when you believe in him and his son,
and yet also this work of sanctification that happens
as we continue to walk in the Lord.
And Paul here is saying that,
man, through these persecutions,
through these sufferings that you are facing,
you are growing in your steadfastness.
You know, Peter would say,
your faith is being refined more than gold.
There's a goodness.
Your character is becoming more like Christ
as you share in his sufferings.
and so here we see this is how the bible portrays persecution that it's always a possibility for
those who are faithfully following the lord that god works in the midst of it he's praiseworthy in
the midst of it and that he uses it for his purposes to refine his people some of us may
not remember i got blasted earlier i was doing the building blocks sermon and i i gave this example
that you're going to hear in a moment and i said something along the lines of like some of you may
be too young to remember that we used to have a coach at the University of Michigan by the name
of Jim Harbaugh. And they were like, bro, that was two years ago. And I'm like, well, there might be
some young people here who did not know, right? And so anyway, there might be some people here who
did not know, but that we used to have a football coach here by the name of Jim Harbaugh. And he was
known to be a little eccentric. He's still eccentric. There's new memes made about him regularly. But
he's a little eccentric. And one thing he did when he came to become our coach was he wanted to change
the perspectives of his players and so some of you may know but what happened was was when during
practice time when these teams ran their drills right whoever won the drill would have to run
extra laps and do more training some of us who've played sports before you know like usually it's
like if you lose you have to do more laps as punishment because you lost but he was like no
you have to change your perspective running and having extra practice it's a opportunity to improve
yourself. And the opportunity to improve yourself only is a privilege for winners. And so he was
trying to change the mentality of the team. And so what used to be viewed as a punishment, running
laps, then became to be viewed as a privilege because this is for people as they get an
opportunity to improve themselves. And I share this because I think when we look at persecution, we
need that kind of change of perspective. I think oftentimes we think of persecution, pain, and
suffering as a punishment from God? What have I been doing wrong that God would make me suffer?
Is God far away that I would have to experience pain like this? And the Bible would say, no,
that's not what is happening. Persecution and suffering is not punishment for you.
I would go as far as to say it is a privilege that God works in our lives through suffering.
If you think I'm crazy, I mean, Acts chapter 5, the apostles are beaten because of their
faith, and they count it as honor.
They're praising and rejoicing in God because they were able to suffer dishonor for his
name.
And I think there's a challenge for us to say, can we change our perspective on persecution,
on pain and suffering?
And instead of viewing it as an undesirable bad thing, can we see it as this is something
that is there, especially if we're seeking to faithfully follow the Lord. And I say this
because this is, you know, a challenge that I have. It's easy for me to assume that I shouldn't have
to suffer that much as I'm trying to faithfully follow the Lord. And yet, we are challenged to
say, no, for as we're following the suffering servant Messiah, it is part of his purposes,
the way that he works, that we also suffer and share in his suffering. Martin Luther has famously
said, you know, our Lord received a crown of thorns. Why do his disciples expect a crown of
roses? I think for us today that you might feel that like there's something in you that feels like
persecution, pain, suffering for the sake of Jesus. I don't want that. And I share these things
because I think for some of us, you know, maybe there's some of us here who feel stuck in your
walk with the Lord. Like you're coming every week to Sunday celebration, you're doing your Bible
reading and your prayer, and you feel like, man, how come I'm not experiencing the fullness of life?
How come I'm not growing the way that I used to? Or how come I'm not close to God the way that
I want to be? And here, I want to challenge us. Have you considered perhaps your unwillingness
to face discomfort and pain for the sake of Christ
is contributing to why you feel so stuck?
Is it possible that you care more about
what your neighbors think,
what your classmates think,
what your coworkers think,
what your family members might think
if you were trying to actually faithfully follow the Lord
in all areas of your life?
Is it possible you're afraid of
what your employers might think,
what your community might think,
what they might do
if you were to be faithful in following him
in all of these areas.
For example, I think, you know, for me,
I think about like, man,
are my neighbors going to think I'm weird
if I talk about God to them all the time?
You know?
Or what will my coworkers think about me?
If I think, well, my coworkers are great.
They're already Christians, I know.
But I imagine for some of us, right, like especially in Ann Arbor, right,
like what will my coworkers think if they know I have a biblical view of marriage and sexuality?
What will my super religious relatives think if they know that I care about the poor?
Will they think I'm too woke or too liberal?
What will the people around me think if they know that I care about both the health and safety of women
and the sanctity of life.
I think these may be questions and things we wrestle with.
And so in order to avoid those discomforts,
we just avoid making any decisions,
doing anything that might rock the boat.
You know, what will my boss think
if I'm not willing to work on Sundays
because I have a commitment to come worship
the living God with his people?
And the scary thing is that
in certain seasons of your life,
maybe you were willing to face the possibility
and potential of persecution.
But I will say as you get older,
sometimes it gets harder. Because as you get older, it's not just like, what will my boss think
if I can't work on Sundays? It's like, what will the other parents think if they know that I'm
teaching my kids a biblical worldview about how the world was created? What will other coaches
think if I say my kid can't come to practice in games on Sunday, right? I think sometimes the fear
and the desire to avoid discomfort and disadvantage for the sake of the kingdom
slowly leads us to compromise in areas of our lives
because our perspective of persecution is that it's just bad,
that suffering is just bad.
And here we're challenged to say,
no, this is the way that God works,
and perhaps you are missing out
on some of the things God wants for you
because you've grown accustomed to compromising in these ways
and avoiding things that might lead
to displeasure, discomfort, and pain.
So that's what we see here first
is that knowing God changes our view of persecution.
Are there areas in your life that you realize, man, maybe I've been compromising
because I just don't want to suffer for God in this way?
And maybe today God wants you to see that might be the very area
that he wants you to take a step of faith, that he could work in there
so that you, like the Thessalonians, might continue to grow in your steadfastness of faith
and in your love for one another.
The second thing we see here is that trusting Jesus gives us hope to face persecution.
It's not just that we need the willingness to face persecution,
but we want encouragement and hope to be able to face it,
that we will be able to be okay even as we suffer for the Lord.
That's what's happening here, right?
Paul is writing to the Thessalonians to encourage them in the midst of their persecution.
The first thing we see here that gives us hope in the midst of persecution
is that God is not blind to our persecution and suffering.
he talks about how when jesus returns god is going to repay he knows who are the afflicted
ones he knows who are the ones doing the afflicting right that god is not unaware of these things
in matthew chapters 5 and 6 jesus talks about you know your heavenly father in heaven sees
what happens in secret he knows the suffering that you're going through for the sake of his name
He knows the ways that you've made sacrifices, right?
Both in private and secret and in public,
God knows the things that you face,
the persecutions and suffering and pain
that you go through for the sake of his name.
And I say that because sometimes
when we think about pain and persecution,
we think like, man, God must be so far away.
Like God must not care.
God must be unaware of these things to let it happen.
But here we see, no, God knows these things.
And he doesn't know your pains and persecutions
like a security guard looking at security monitors.
It's not like he's just far away.
God knows your sufferings in an intimate and personal way.
That's what we see in the person of Jesus Christ.
That God the Son comes so that God himself knows what it is to experience human suffering.
God himself knows what it is to be unjustly abused, hurt, persecuted against.
God knows your suffering.
God knows that you are suffering.
That's our first encouragement, that the God that we trust, the God who is powerful and who is over us,
He knows the persecutions and pains that we go through as we seek to follow Him.
And even more so, the second thing we see is that Jesus will justly judge the persecution and the suffering that we face.
We see here first that He will provide relief.
I'm sorry, let me go back one second.
what's really interesting about this passage it's easy to miss but throughout the old testament
there's all this language about the day of the lord some of you might be familiar with it and
the idea is that the day of the lord or the day of yahweh is the day that god is gonna come and that
he is gonna bring salvation for his people and just punishment for their enemies it's like throughout
the the prophets throughout the old testament there's this idea that we have hope as we wait
for the day of the lord and here what paul is doing is all of this language about the day of
the lord he's applying it to jesus he's saying jesus jesus is the god you are waiting for to
come to return to bring this justice and salvation and here what he's saying is he's going to do that
by one he's going to be providing relief he says that when jesus comes with his mighty angels
in flaming fire. He's going to come and he will provide relief to those who are experiencing
persecution and pain for the sake of his name, right? And this is the hope that he gives us,
is that one day there will be an end to all the pain and suffering, all the sacrifice, all the
difficulties that you face for the sake of his name. Some of us are familiar with how John paints
this in revelations 21 right he says uh you know behold the dwelling place of god is with man he
will dwell with them and they will be his people and god himself will be like them as their god he
will wipe away every tear from their eyes and death shall be no more neither shall there be
mourning nor crying nor pain anymore for the former things have passed away here we have this
promise of relief, that when we choose to follow God faithfully and as we experience persecution
and pain as a result of that, that's not forever. There is a final rest and relief that we have
that we will have when Jesus returns. Now, you might be thinking, Pastor Sam, that's a long
time away. We don't even know when that's going to happen, right? Like, man, I want relief now.
But I would contend that the kind of relief you're looking for, that there's different times when relief is appropriate, and there's different times when relief and rest is not.
Not too long ago, we had the World Cup, right?
Some of y'all saw that?
Okay.
Yeah.
Imagine you're in the World Cup.
You're playing there.
You're representing your country.
You're doing your thing, right?
I know it's tiring.
I heard, like, the average, during an average match, people run, like, 7 to 12 miles or something like that.
Like, that's a lot of miles.
That's a lot of running.
That's a lot of pain.
That's a lot of difficulty.
And I'm sure people want rest and relief during that time.
But it would be inappropriate if in the middle of the match, you're like, ah, coach, I'm tired.
And you go in the middle of the match to the locker room, change into your pajamas, and then go sleep in your bed.
Like, that would be just, this is a wrong time to seek relief, right?
The relief comes at the end of 90 minutes plus stoppage time.
When the final whistle blows, that is when you get the relief.
You've left everything on the field or the pitch, whatever.
You've left everything there, and that is the right time to experience the rest that you were looking for.
That's what Paul's saying here.
Yes, there is relief and rest in the Christian life.
Jesus says, come to me all who are weary and heavy laden.
Of course, we have times for rest and relief.
But the real deep relief and rest you're looking for, it will come when Jesus returns.
And Paul is giving this promise and encouragement to the Thessalonians to say,
your suffering, that's not eternal.
It's not permanent, right?
That is for a time.
And when Jesus comes, he will repay.
He will justly give you the rest that you need and desire.
That's one part of the hope that we have when Jesus returns.
The other part is that he will repay.
He will repay.
That those people who are persecuting, that they will get their just reward.
That he will come and that they will be afflicted with affliction
and that they will experience eternal destruction away from his presence.
One thing I want you to notice here is that this picture of God's punishment
and God's eternal destruction for those who don't know him
men who do not obey the gospel, it is not used here to scare people. And I say that because if
you grew up in church or around church, you may be familiar with this idea of eternal judgment.
And oftentimes it's presented as like, it's like to scare you, to say like, oh shoot, I don't want
eternal judgment and destruction. I want good stuff. Like, let me choose, you know, let me choose
Jesus because I don't want to face that, right? And so definitely not at HMCC Youth Group, but
maybe in your other youth, you've experienced that kind of scare tactic where the eternal judgment
of God was used to scare you into trusting Jesus. Maybe just me. Okay, fine. Here, that's not what
Paul's doing, right? Paul is saying that the eternal destruction of evildoers, of those who
don't obey God and don't know God, that is a reason for hope. That is a reason for encouragement.
And the way he's saying is that there is no one who has done you wrong, who has persecuted you,
and offended you, and hurt you, harmed you, because you trust in Jesus,
there's no one who does these unjust things to you that will go away unscathed, right?
There's no injustice, no persecution caused, no affliction caused that will be unaccounted for.
When Jesus returns, all evil and all sin will be appropriately condemned.
And that is a reason for hope, right?
That when we see, not only persecution when we're talking about, even general injustice in the world,
there will be a day when the perfect judgment and justice of God will make sure that all those who have done wrong
will experience the just punishments for that.
And that should give you hope.
That any injustice that you have experienced, any injustice in the world,
it will be called into account and judged by the perfect justice of Christ.
So now as we think about it, you might be like, okay, okay, Pastor Sam, but eternal destruction sounds kind of harsh, if you're asking me.
To which I would say, nobody asked you.
But what I really would say is, no, just take a moment to think about it, right?
I think we can think, oh, like, God, that sounds really harsh.
Like, I don't think I would do it that way.
But I would contend to you that there is no better justice
than the justice that comes from the hand and the heart and the mind
of an eternal, unchanging, perfect, and holy God.
Right?
Think about the alternatives, right?
I mean, the things that you think are bad today and worthy of punishment,
a thousand years ago, maybe most people didn't think it was that bad.
And the things that you think are not that bad today,
maybe a thousand years ago, people actually thought it was really bad.
If we are depending just on human preference, human understanding for what is punishable, what is bad and wrong,
I mean, that is changing all the time, not only throughout history, but even around the world, right?
If we're looking at human consensus for what judgment and justice is, we will never get an appropriate response.
But here we have the hope of a God who has never changed,
a God who is unbiased,
a God who he himself created all things and is good.
He is the one who decides what is just,
what is good and bad and worthy of punishment.
So part of the challenge for us is to say,
can we trust that God's judgment and justice
is the best and is good, right?
That is how God's judgment becomes hope for us,
to say, wow, the infinite, good, perfect God.
He is going to judge justly when he returns.
And so all this injustice I see, all the pain and suffering I've experienced, I see around the world,
that will be accounted for when he returns.
Now the last thing, the last thing that might bother you,
maybe you're not that bothered, but anyway, yeah.
It could be possible.
You're like, Pastor Sam, I thought Christianity was about grace.
You're not talking about grace.
And just as, that's not what Paul's talking about either, to be fair.
But what is happening here, right, is Paul is trying to say he's giving us reasons for encouragement to face injustice and persecution.
So that's why he's focusing on the punishment that evildoers will deserve.
But I would say to you, even here, the fact that there is grace and hope is implied.
It's implied.
And why do I say that?
because the person telling you that those who afflict Christians in the church will face judgment
is Paul. And if you know anything about Paul, he used to be a persecutor, right? So he's not,
when he's saying that there's eternal judgment against those who afflict Christians, he's not
saying that's the, like everyone who has ever done anything wrong against the church, anyone
who has not obeyed the gospel is done. He's saying there's only two ways that justice works.
either you will be held accountable for every way you have fallen short every way that you have not
obeyed God every way you do not know and acknowledge the Lord in your life and you will experience
eternal judgment for that or implied in his own testimony is that you trust in the Lord Jesus
who suffered on your behalf we sang about he took all of that judgment on the cross
for those people who believed in him and therefore justice is still rightly
handed out, but instead of you receiving that, Jesus Christ has received it for you. And that's
what gives the Thessalonians hope, right? Because if we're honest, even as we think about this,
the categories of afflicted and afflictor is not that clear. Like, there are times I'm sure that
you have experienced injustice at the hands of other people and suffering at the hands of other
people. But I would also guess there are times when you have been the person inflicting unjust
suffering on someone else i say that as an older sibling i'm sure it has happened i know it's
happened in my life right and so what is the hope the hope is not that you are perfectly on the side
of the afflicted and therefore when jesus returns you'd be like oh yes the whole time i never did
anything wrong and i was just wondering who was afflicted no the hope is that all those who do
not obey all those who do not know and acknowledge god it's those and those who in their humility
as they realize, man, I have just as much potential
to be the afflictor as much as the afflicted.
But by God's grace, he has helped me to see my need for him
and I trust in him.
And it's that he's going to receive
all the judgment I deserve.
And now I can be empowered and encouraged
to follow him faithfully.
So that's what we see here is that, man,
there is hope for us to face persecution
as we think about Jesus Christ,
what he has done and what he will do when he returns.
And all of this leads us to the last point, which is that depending on God helps us to
live fully in the midst of persecution.
In these last few verses, we see Paul pray for those who are in the midst of persecution.
And here what we see is that we can dream big even in the midst of persecution and suffering.
Paul is praying that their every resolve for good may be fulfilled by the power of God,
that every work of faith would be fulfilled by the power of God,
even in the midst of their persecution and suffering.
He's saying that all of the things, the good things that they desire for the Lord,
he's praying that that would happen by the power of God,
even as they face difficulty and pain and suffering in this world.
And one thing that's cool here is that he's not just saying like individually,
you, you, you, you, you, you, you, I hope your dreams may be fulfilled,
but he's saying your dreams plural.
your resolve, desire for good, your work of faith as a church, he's praying, that would be fulfilled
even as you are facing persecution and suffering together. I wonder, what would it be like for HMCC
of Ann Arbor that God would work every resolve for good that we have, that every work of faith
that we undertake together as a church, that God would bring those things to fruition even as we
are willing to face potential persecution i think it's hard being a bible believing christ-exalting
god-loving church in the context that we're in but what would it look like for god to say that
even and maybe especially because you are in this context and still holding on to me
as you are depending on me that i will work out these things your resolve for good the things that
you want to see happen for your neighbors the nations and the next generation the things that
you are already doing and praying for, that God would do those things even as you are willing to
face persecution and suffering in your life, all for the glory of God. And that's why, that's why
it's important for us to be willing to face pain and discomfort, persecution and suffering, because
it's not just you, but as a church, we could experience these things as we are willing to
trust in the Lord, as we're willing to trust in his perfect judgment, as we're willing to trust
in his enabling power and grace.
All of these things, as we consider it,
we realize, man, it is a good and worthy thing
to be willing to suffer for the one
who has already suffered for us.
Brothers and sisters, I say this too.
I mean, I had to think real hard
because I think we are not accustomed
to suffering and persecution that much.
But also, as we preach this, I mean,
the reality is this is what is happening
all around the world,
even at this very moment.
There are brothers and sisters in Christ
around the world who are,
who have paid that cost,
who are bearing their cross
to say, I'm willing to suffer
and experience persecution
for the great name of Jesus Christ.
Whether it's in sub-Saharan Africa,
whether it's in Southeast Asia, East Asia,
whether it's in the Middle East,
all around the world,
there are Christians who are suffering
for the sake and name of Jesus Christ.
Let us be a people.
but may we not be sitting on the sidelines
as our brothers and sisters around the world
are experiencing that.
May we also not seek out suffering for suffering's sake,
but may we also live our lives,
surrender to the Lord,
willing to face even potential persecution
for the sake of his name,
so that we might follow in the footsteps of him
who suffered for us.
Hebrews chapter 12, verse two says,
that we look to Jesus,
the founder and perfecter of our faith,
who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross,
despising the shame, and is seated at the right hand of the throne of God.
Jesus, for the joy of knowing your salvation,
the good pleasure of God, all of these things,
he suffered for us.
Let us be people who follow in his footsteps.
Let us be people who are saying, willing for the joy,
for the fullness of life that God has.
Let us be willing to face these things for his name and for his glory.
That's why the one thing for today is that Jesus' return gives us hope to face persecution and live more fully for God.
Let us pray.
Father, we come to you today, and Lord, we thank you.
We thank you that you are not far from us in the midst of suffering.
We thank you that you use even bad things like pain and persecution for your good purposes.
Lord, we ask today that you would give us discernment to see areas of our lives,
where we have perhaps compromised
and have been shying away.
Lord, we ask that you would help us
to see you as more worthy,
to see you as more good,
more glorious, God,
that we would be willing to suffer for you.
Lord, we pray as well,
maybe there are people here
who are experiencing that now,
that as they're trying to follow you faithfully,
that there's the pushback,
there's discomfort and pain
that they're experiencing.
Lord, we pray that you would encourage
and strengthen them today,
that you would give them eyes
to see the good things
and the work that you're doing
in their lives in the midst of that.
and Lord we pray for those
brothers and sisters
all around the world
who are persecuted
we pray that you would
strengthen and comfort them
and then use them
to testify of your goodness
and of your gospel
to the nations
even as we seek
to do that here
Lord we pray
would you work in us
help us to see you
more clearly
help us to trust you
more deeply
help us to step out
in faith
and God may you work
in this church
in our lives
to fulfill
our resolves for good
and the works of faith that we have started.
Lord, we thank you.
We look to you.
We trust you.
Pray all these things in Jesus' name.
Amen.